Guide to the Faithfull family Papers, 1864-1887 and undated RL.11547
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Faithfull family papers
1864-1887 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Faithfull family
RL.11547
0.1 Linear Feet 22 items
The Faithful family focuses on the family of Rev. Ferdinand Faithfull and Elizabeth Mary Harrison of Headley Rectory in Surrey, England, and their eight children. Among the children were Esther Faithfull Fleet (1823–1908), who was both a book illustrator and the mother of seven children. The youngest child, Emily Faithfull (1836?-1895), was an feminist reformer, philanthropist, printer, publisher, novelist, and lecturer. Collection comprises 14 letters, an envelope autographed by Emily Faithfull, an invitation completed by her, a printed invitation acceptance, a carte de visite and two copies of a mounted albumen photograph of her, along with two illustrated pieces completed by Esther Faithfull Fleet.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically
Biographical / Historical
The Faithful family focuses on the family of Rev. Ferdinand Faithfull and Elizabeth Mary Harrison of Headley Rectory in Surrey, England, and their eight children. Among the children were Esther Faithfull Fleet (1823–1908), who was both a book illustrator and the mother of seven children, including John Faithfull Fleet, a noted historian and Indologist; George Rutland Fleet, a successful actor; and Herbert Cecil Fleet, a Vice-Admiral. The youngest child, Emily Faithfull (1836?-1895), was an feminist reformer, philanthropist, printer, publisher, novelist, and lecturer. She established the Victoria Press in London in 1860, which employed female compositors, and was appointed printer and publisher in ordinary to Queen Victoria in 1862. She published the "Englishwoman's Journal" and "The Victoria Magazine."
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Faithfull family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2015 and as a gift in 2018.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises 14 letters, an envelope autographed by Emily Faithfull, an invitation completed by her, a printed invitation acceptance, a carte de visite and two copies of a mounted albumen photograph of her, along with two illustrated pieces completed by Esther Faithfull Fleet. The letters, all written by Emily Faithfull, include routine correspondence and thank you notes; other topics include the capacity of Victoria Press to do law work; an honor bestowed on her by the professional women's organization, Sorosis, in New York; a statement in the Guardian newspaper claiming that in a speech she repudiated women's rights as it applied to her work; a request for early assistance with preparations for Christmas in order to provide relief for "some very distressing cases;" and inquiries regarding the printing of her "Jubilee Address" or its distribution. There is one letter to Henry Ward Beecher asking him to hand out notices regarding her upcoming lecture, and mentioning Lucretia Mott's plans to address the audience. Several letters feature the stamp or embossed stamp of the Victoria Press. The carte de visite was produced by the London Stereoscopic & Photography Co., and the mounted photographs by W. & D. Downey of Ebury Street, London. The illustrated pieces completed by Esther Faithfull Fleet include a calling card hand decorated in ink and watercolors (?), and a watercolor painting of a parrot.
Women's rights -- England -- History -- 19th century; Cartes-de-visite photographs (card photographs); Albumen prints; Watercolors (paintings); Faithfull family; Faithfull, Emily, 1836?-1895; Faithfull, Emily, 1836?-1895 -- Correspondence; Fleet, Esther Faithfull; Beecher, Henry Ward, 1813-1887; Victoria Press (London, England); Sorosis (New York, N.Y.); Baskin, Lisa Unger; Lisa Unger Baskin Collection (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library); Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- Letter, Faithfull, Emily to Beecher, Mr.., 1864 April 9 (Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Autograph note signed Emily Faithfull, responding to an inquiry about the capacity of the Victoria Press to do "law work"
- Letter, Faithfull, Emily to Madam, 1869 July 27 (Folder 1)
  Autograph letter signed Emily Faithfull, regarding an honor bestowed upon her by the ladies of Sorosis; mentions her desire to visit New York to "make the personal acquaintance of Ladies who have done so much on that side of the water to advance the cause"
  with stamp of the Victoria Press
- Letter, Faithfull, Emily to Walford, W., 1869 October 9th (Folder 1)
  A letter from Emily Faithful originally enclosed in the book, 'Mariquita' by Henry Grant, regarding Walford's statement in the Guardian that she repudiated Women's Rights as applied to her own work
- Letter, Faithfull, Emily to Sir, 1869 November 15 (Folder 1)
  Autograph note signed Emily Faithfull, asking for help setting up a lecture at the Guildhall in Bath
  with the stamp of the Victoria Press
- Letter, Faithfull, Emily to Walford, Mr., 1872 May 21st (Folder 1)
  Letter requesting Walford to return the volumes of Victoria that she lent him
- Letter, Faithfull, Emily to Booth, Miss, 1872 October 31 (Folder 1)
  Autograph note signed Emily Faithfull, mentions an upcoming trip to Brooklyn and Chicago (her first trip to the United States)
  with embossed stamp of Victoria Press
- Letter, Faithfull, Emily to Beecher, Mr. [Henry Ward], 1873 March 28 (Folder 1)
  Autograph letter signed Emily Faithfull, to Beecher, asking him to announce her upcoming visit and lecture, written towards the end of her first trip to America, mentioning a farewell lecture "to this land of promise", with "Lucretia Mott in attendance"
  the second leaf describes her talk: "Work for women with her English & American experiences" at Steinway Hall on April 3rd
  with embossed stamp of the Victoria Press.
- Letter, Faithfull, Emily, 1874 April 14 (Folder 1)
  A note from Emily Faithfull originally enclosed in a copy of 'POEMS: An Offering to Lancashire.' The note reads:
  "Dear [...],
  Can you call upon me about your paper on Friday or Saturday at 10 o'cl.
  [...]
  Miss Faithfull"
- Letter, Faithfull, Emily to Madam, 1880 October 23 (Folder 1)
  Autograph note signed Emily Faithfull requesting early assistance with preparations for Christmas in order to provide relief for "some very distressing cases."
- Lettter, Faithfull, Emily to Booth, Miss, 1882 April 19 (Folder 1)
  Autograph note signed Emily Faithfull, stating what a pleasure it was to learn about her through mutual friends
- Letter, Faithfull, Emily to 'Dear Sir', 1887 March 21 - March 24 (Folder 1)
  Two letters to an unnamed party inquiring about publishing Faithfull's "Jubilee Address" on Queen Victoria.
- Letter, Faithfull, Emily to Madam, 1887 May 7 (Folder 1)
  Autograph note signed Emily Faithfull, probably a response to a printing order
- Letter, Faithfull, Emily to My dear "John", January 9, no year (Folder 1)
  Autograph signed letter by Emily Faithful mentioning the pleasure of meeting a girl for which she wrote a "sentiment." Gift of Jane Williamson.
- Emily Faithfull autographed envelope, undated (Folder 1)
- Emily Faithful printed invitation acceptance, 1883 November 5 (Folder 1)
- Emily Faithfull invitation, undated (Folder 1)
- Emily Fathfull carte de visite, undated (Folder 1)
- Emily Faithfull albumen photograph, undated; 2 copies (Folder 1)
- Esther Faithfull Fleet watercolor painting of a parrot, undated (Folder 1)
- Esther Faithful Fleet illustrated calling card, undated (Folder 1)